We're back for another episode of The
Centrifuge,
where we spin out the BS from the real
information discussed on health shows.
My name is Nick. I hold a PhD in
molecular medicine, and I'm tired of
listening to health podcasts that don't
supply studies to verify what is correct
and what is BS. So, here we are. I'll do
it for you. Today, we're going to be
focused on the amino acid glycine as
discussed by proclaimed glycine expert,
Dr. Joel Brind who is a professor with a
PhD in biomedical sciences like me and
has a lot of work in the specific field
of endocrinology. Now he was recently on
the Rethink Health podcast with Dr.
Autumn Smith who has her doctorate in
holistic nutrition. So in this podcast
episode I stumbled upon Dr. Brian
discusses these topics. One, the problem
with current day science. Number two,
why vegans tend to be healthier and why
carnivores might achieve the same if
they eat nose totail. And three, obesity
and cardiovascular disease are caused by
glycine deficiency. Now, you'll want to
stick around for the last one because
you'll be shocked but by what I found on
that front. Anyway, you will find all
studies that I'll be going over in the
description. Now, without further ado,
let's spin it up. But I just want to
highlight to the implications like you
said where is the state of the research
in terms of you know you have to
establish a lot of things is there an
association people with lower levels do
they have higher risk of certain things
and then you have supplementation like
tell us about what you think are the
strongest pieces of evidence pertaining
to actual conditions we might experience
like heart disease or dementia I've
>> Oh yes there's some that are you know uh
that are probably uh
very telling about the the stat the
status of science. So what I would say
now is there's a lot of research that's
been around for a long time which really
shows what the truth is which really uh
evidences what the real actors are and
what they're doing. But the the state of
science is not very good. Why? Because
the state of sec technology is great.
People may have noticed in other realms
that as the technology improves the
competence of the core field declines.
Right. The
>> more you have AI, what do you think is
going to happen to writing skills the
more AI takes over?
>> You know, I I can't even get into my
email that it doesn't say, "Oh, hi. I
can help you write this. Excuse me. I
think I I think I can say, "Thank you
very much." [laughter]
>> And a few other simple things in an
email without AI popping into my screen
and saying, "Oh, let me write this for
you." No, but anyway, that's what
happened. So in science there used to be
uh science pure science was you start
you make an observation and you think
something's going on you have a so you
have a question and an answer to that
question you think of a hypothesis so
then you have to think of how you're
going to test this hypothesis and then
you run think of an experiment you run
the experiment you get the data and then
finally you have your answer. Well,
uh, nowadays they call that
hypothesis-based science. In the old
days, we used to call that science.
[laughter]
Nowadays, they have what they call
databased science. They have all these
all these disciplines, all these tools
they call omix, metabolomics and
genomics and proteomics and lipomics.
What are those? Those are are uh
devices. There's systems now where you
can measure hundreds of things at the
same time. So instead of trying to test
the hypothesis that substance XYZ may be
a good marker for diabetes and so let's
test people's blood for substance XYZ
and maybe a couple of other things.
Well, okay, maybe we'll get a grant to
fund the research and we'll run the
experiment. We'll do it. That's fine.
Nowadays, you can me well we'll measure
300 different metabolites at the same
time. We'll measure hundreds of
different gene products. We'll do you
know metabolomics and genomics and we'll
and then we'll compare let's say people
who don't have the disease with people
who have diabetes or some other disease.
Throw it all into the computer and let
the computer decide what's significant
and what isn't in terms of differences
between the the patients and the
controls and then let's try and figure
out why. So they start with the data and
that's really not science at all. what
they call database science. In the old
days, they used to call that a fishing
expedition. And nobody would ever pay to
do a fishing expedition because you you
couldn't have enough money and enough
blood to test for all those things you
need to test for cuz you don't really
know what you're looking for. You're
just on a fishing expedition. I'm
including this because I wanted you to
hear Dr. Smith's question and I try not
to edit things out when a person is
speaking. A lot of this, as you know, is
opinion. I think that Dr. Brian brings
up some good points. For example, he's
right that in the past before we had the
technology that we do now, we had to be
a lot more linear about things. I think
X will happen if we manipulate Y, i.e. a
hypothesis. However, recently to Dr.
Brian's point, we have these wonderful
technologies that allow us to take blood
samples or a tissue sample and then we
can measure across thousands of
molecules what is present or not present
and the amount between a sick population
and a healthy population. Now, it
doesn't surprise me that someone might
call that a fishing exped expedition,
which means that you're just shotgunning
many bullets in the dark and hoping that
something hits. However, this type of
research has sped up research progress
immensely, multiple orders of magnitude,
because it just makes sense to use
what's known as unargeted omix data,
which supplies thousands of data points.
And then the few molecules that are the
most different between the healthy and
the sick people are then the targets for
manipulation. I mean, think about the
alternative. The alternative is that you
don't know the molecules, thousands of
them. So, you look at each one
individually, and that could literally
take you years, what is now done in just
a few days. Now, it's incredible
technology, and I'm of the mind that
it's massively improved our ability to
target particular molecules that are
most suspiciously different between
groups. It just makes sense. Either way,
I can respect Dr. Brian's perspective,
even if I disagree. Although, as a quick
nod, I can also certainly see how AI can
get in the way of developing personal
skills like writing. Still, that's
beside the point. Let's move on to
carnivores and vegans. This won't be
inflammatory in any way whatsoever.
>> So, now is lots of things of fishing
expedition. So one was in the uh the uh
the so-called epic trial European uh
physiology some some acronym for a very
big set of studies done with a European
consortium of many universities and one
in the UK were studying amino acids and
so they wanted to say what's the
difference between vegans lactovearians
fish eating vegetarians and omnivores
meateers what's the difference in their
amino acids so they measured the amino
amino acids of 100 in each cate
category. How many of each amino acid do
they consume every day in their diet
which they followed very carefully and
measured very closely. And then they
measured the blood serum, the blood
plasma of everybody to find out what
were the amino acids in the blood. And
so guess what? The ones who ate more
lysine had more lysine in their bloods.
The one who ate more uh histadine had
more histadine in their blood. And it
all seemed to work out fine except when
it came to one little pesky amino acid,
glycine. And what was that? Well, for
some reason, the meateers who had more
of every amino acid because they had a
much higher protein content in the diet,
a much higher protein intake, guess
what? They had the least amount of
glycine in their blood. Remember, more
methionine uses up glycine.
>> They didn't think about that, even
though that was in the literature also.
And guess who had the most glycine in
their blood? The vegans.
>> No.
>> This explains why decades and decades of
research have shown, oh yes, it's much
better to be a vegan than a meat eater
because the protein content is different
and plant proteins are better for you
and all that. Well, it's just because
when they do the animal proteins, they
throw out the bones and the connective
tissues. But when you eat the whole
animal, you don't get those effects of
glycine deficiency, more inflammation,
more heart disease, more cancer, and
earlier demise because you have the
whole protein in there. But these
people, they could not explain why the
vegans had more glycine in their blood
and the meateers who ate more glycine
than anybody else had the least amount
of glycine in their blood by about 20%.
These are substantial differences. Okay,
this is a big one to cover. The claim is
multi-layered. One part is that vegans
have more glycine in their blood, this
amino acid Dr. Bryant focuses on, which
gives them better health outcomes. Now,
the second layer is that people who eat
meat, like carnivores, could narrow the
health playing field if they just ate
nose totail. Meaning, not just the meat,
but the tendons, the ligaments, the
bones, and well, I mean, everything. The
natural step is to open up this study
because Dr. Brian kindly offered a
citation, a rare thing in many podcasts,
though it's sometimes not feasible off
the top of your head. Anyway, I found
the study, the EPIC study, and sure
enough, it shows a comparison of four
different groups, exactly like he
described. If we look at the blood
levels of all the amino acids between
the four groups listed up top, you'll
see a bunch of numbers. Now, don't
worry. We can ignore most of it. We'll
just focus on this line, glycine. The
researchers have used the meateers as
the reference group. The other three
groups are compared against. All we need
to know is that the vegan group had a
blood glycine of 452 and the meateers
had a value of 390. And yes, the
differences were statistically
confirmed. So this confirms Dr. Brian's
point that vegans, at least in this
study, have greater blood glycine
levels. Now, it's also true that
generally people who eat more
plant-based foods, as vegans do, tend to
have lower risk of a series of different
diseases. However, one major issue, if
we return to this overwhelming table,
you'll note that the glycine is not the
only amino acid difference between the
groups. So, this study does not provide
any evidence that glycine is the main
factor for why mostly plant-based
consumers have relatively lower rates of
disease and death. It was also never
designed to assess that question. Of
course, it's not like Dr. Bryant is
making a statement based on this study
alone. Now, to loop in a second related
claim related to meateers, would be
better off if they didn't restrict their
intake to just meat, but actually ate
more glycine through bone, cartilage,
and the like. Now, the reason that Dr.
Bryant is mentioning this is because
there's this idea that another amino
acid methionine uses up significant
amounts of glycine. This has been known
for several decades now. For example,
this study where methane given to
animals completely rob their liver of
glycine. This is all important because
there's some theories out there that
center around the overabundance of
methane in the cells leading to faster
aging and the risk of disease. And since
methane is in high concentrations in
many meats, this would be the reason for
this increased risk of aging and
disease. So Dr. Brian's suggestion is
that we should increase glycine intake,
which can be found in bone and
collaginous tissues like cartilage. This
increased glycine would protect us from
having too much methane if you're
consuming a primarily animal-based diet
like carnivore individuals are. Now, as
far as increased glycine, reducing
methane levels, there's some truth to
that. As we went over, the issue is that
the assumption that the cause of these
diseases and mortality risks are due to
insufficient glycine alone are a far
stretch because they're hyperfocused on
one amino acid. Yet, as we saw, many
amino acids are different between meat
eaters and vegans. And that's just
considering differences in amino acids
from protein sources. We're not even
discussing differences in fat content,
iron, and plenty of other molecules that
are different between animal-based foods
and plant-based foods. Just as an aside,
these reviews that I'm citing here
aren't proof that I'm correct. They're
just proof that many researchers
identify and describe other mechanisms
that are at play. That's all. So, is it
possible that a carnivore or generally
anyone who eats meat could have a better
health profile if they ate more
cartilage, bone, and the like compared
to if they didn't? Absolutely. However,
that still doesn't mean that glycine is
the one missing key. The point here
being that the claims extend beyond what
the research would agree with. It's
possible that glycine could play a
factor, but it is unlikely that it is
the only factor. And in fact, we're
about to see why in our last section,
which had some pretty shocking
discoveries. Now, before we touch on
that, I'll be getting more into the
methane connection to glycine, as well
as getting into more detail on several
studies on glycine in the extended
version of this video that you're
currently watching. If you're looking
for a one-stop research shop, then check
out my premium research platform,
including all of these perks right here.
It's called the Physionic Insiders. The
link to join is in the description.
>> So, this is one of the problems is so
there it is. It was what they needed to
know to connect the dots. They were in
the literature already. But, you know,
for like 20, 30 years, but they but
these people are just interested in
amino acids and they're so specialized.
Everything is, you know, we used to tell
a joke back in the in our high school
days, you know, that with specialization
is that you as you as you go on in your
educational career, you learn more and
more about less and less until you know
everything about nothing. And this is
this is what the practice of medicine
has become and nutrition nutrition more
has more people who think holistically
you know like you know you're one whole
individual and you're eating all these
things and everything needs to be
integrated together the way your body
does it. So that's one of the one of the
pieces of research that I like to
highlight as a particular thing. But
there lots of papers show the connection
with diabetes with obesity now some of
the most exciting research and it's
exciting because I'm starting to inter
interest the cardiologists in my family.
>> Nice. And that that is a big deal
because some uh cardiologists at the
Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota and
also in Jacksonville, Florida were
studying childhood obesity
epidemic, right? Childhood obesity in
this country. And um and so they had a
very interesting hypothesis. I said you
know that of course obesity is
associated with all manner of you know
uh morbidity you know uh and heart
attack and stroke and diabetes and all
of that but you know when they're kids
they don't get it. So, let's see if we
can look for markers in their blood of
these obese kids and see if we can find
something if they're the same patterns
that we find in older people who
actually have diseases like heart
disease. In this case, they're looking
at cardiovascular disease. So,
cardiovascular disease is characterized
by a number of metabolic markers. and
let's see if we can find the metabolic
changes, the biochemical changes in the
blood of these kids while they're kids
and before they have any of these
cardiovascular diseases. And guess what?
>> Glycine. And that with other literature,
other experiments that people have done
are showing that obesity shuts down
glycine synthesis. So yes, your body
makes it, but it doesn't make enough.
But also, when you're obese, you're
making less. So your glycine deficiency
is exacerbated even more. All right, the
claim here is that glycine deficiency is
linked to diabetes, cardiovascular
disease, obesity, and more. Now, Dr.
Bryant again references some research,
thankfully, where he mentions the Mayo
Clinic and the fact that it's in obese
kids and they were looking at heart
disease markers. Now, I did a bit of
soouththing and I believe I may have
found the study and confirming Dr.
Brian's point. Low blood glycine was
associated in children with greater
concentrations of known cardiovascular
risk factors like insulin resistance.
You can see that as the line moves to
the right that's greater homir which is
an insulin resistance measure and the
vertical axis is the blood glycine
concentration. Okay, fair enough. But
we're actually butddting up against the
same problem as before. We're looking at
associations that are not properly
controlled. And there are many other
factors that also associate with
increased insulin resistance. But
instead of restarting the previous
argument, let me show you some less than
comforting signs related to glycine and
health. I'm talking about studies like
these that show an increased risk of
stroke related mortality from greater
glycine consumption. This would
certainly fly in the face of this
argument that glycine is the defender
against disease and would even mean that
greater glycine consumption is related
to more harm. Not exactly comforting. My
point here isn't to scare glycine
consumers half to death, though maybe
their glycine is already doing that for
them. No, I kid. My point is Dr. Brian's
confidence in glycine is whole and
unwavering. Yet, the research indicates
that there's questions yet to be
answered. So, should we put all our
faith in this, in my opinion, relatively
arbitrary amino acid, I'd argue against
it. That said, to quiet some of the
grumblings coming my way, there are
direct lines of evidence that glycine is
beneficial across multiple randomized
control trials. So, should you overly be
worried about uh this one study linking
glycine to stroke risk? probably not as
more evidence points towards glycine's
benefits. So in the bigger picture, Dr.
Brian's points about glycine are
consistently focused on associative
data, which is fine, but are difficult
to control for all other potential
factors when you're looking at a single
amino acid. So yes, low glycine may
track with cardiovascular disease risk
factors and other diseases, but that
likely does not account for all the
other factors that also contribute to
these diseases. In the end, we can go
part of the way with Dr. Brian's
assertions, but not as completely or as
assured. This is what the data shows up
to now. One, yes, people who eat
plant-based nutrition tend to have
greater blood glycine levels. Two, even
if glycine plays a role in why people
struggle with diseases, it is unlikely
to be the only factor. There are many
others that researchers offer and these
factors tend to have much more research
behind them. Three, glycine supplement
supplementation is even with several
holes in the literature that need to be
patched likely beneficial for our health
based on several randomized control
trials. In fact, some of those benefits
like on sleep can be found right here.
Or if you want more analysis from this
podcast on glycine, I have another
episode launching next week which I'll
put right here when it releases. Links
are also in the description. Thanks for
tuning in to yet another episode of the
centeruge. I'll see you in the next one.
Bye.